CAPITAL AREA COUNCIL OF CHURCHES RECORDS (APAP129) 1941-2002
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Capital Area Council of Churches Records1941-2002
nam_apap129
Capital Area Council Of Churches
9
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
This collection contains administrative files, correspondence, newsletters, subject files and meeting minutes from the Capital Area Council of Churches, an organization designed to promote cooperation between different religious institutions in the Albany, N.Y. area.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by the Capital Area Council of Churches in January 2002.
Organizational Sketch
The Capital Area Council of Churches (CACC) was founded in 1941 as the Federation of Churches of Christ in Albany, N.Y. and Vicinity. The name was changed to the CACC as part of the adoption of a new organizational constitution submitted for approval to the Annual Meeting in June 1958. The preliminary considerations for forming this organization had been discussed among four Albany area clergymen: the Rev. William H. McConaghy of the Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, the Rev. Erville Maynard of St. Peter's Episcopal Church, the Rev. Arthur Adams of the First Presbyterian Church and Dr. Kenneth B. Wells of the Westminster Presbyterian Church. These discussions culminated in a meeting of area congregation representatives on April 4, 1941 when a "meeting of Clergy and Laity" was held "to consider a proposal for the establishment of a City Federation of Churches in Albany, N.Y." (Minutes, April 4, 1941.) The first meeting was chaired by the Rev. M. Stephen James who summarized earlier, efforts to organize and credited Mr. Benton S. Hoit with the exploratory work of a draft constitution. Three of these organizational meetings were held in 1941 resulting in the official incorporation of the Federation of Churches of Christ in Albany, New York, and Vicinity on January 12, 1942.
The Federation was intended to encompass, absorb, coordinate and extend the community service and ministry functions of several existing organizations including the Albany Protestant Welfare Society (House of Friendship), the Albany City Council of Religious Education, the State College Christian Association, the Federation of Youth, and the Ministerial Association. These organizations continued to operate under their own names, but were brought to varying degrees under the organizational and financial umbrella of the Federation. Later additional affiliations included: the Council of Church Women of Albany in January 1944; Chapel House (Albany Collegiate Interfaith Center) on December 16, 1966, and the Seaman's Agency of Albany (the Port Ministry) in 1978.
As stated in its Constitution of 1948, "The particular objects for which this organization is formed are to develop the spirit of Christian fellowship and to promote through cooperative effort the spiritual, moral, social and civic welfare of the community." Rewording in later revisions elaborates and specifies. The CACC administration currently consists of four officers: President, Vice-President, Recording Secretary and Treasurer and a Council Assembly consisting of the clergy and two lay persons from each member congregation (previously there were additional representatives for those congregations larger than a certain size), and the director and two members of other member organizations. They are governed by a Board of Directors consisting of the four officers, committee chairs and a maximum of twelve members-at-large chosen from local laity and clergy of member congregations. Earlier constitutions included one member of each communion in place of the members-at-large. Operational responsibilities are handled by an Executive Committee consisting of the four officers (previously including division chairs and department chairs) with daily administrative responsibilities residing with an Executive Director hired by the Executive Committee.
As of the date of transition from the Federation to the Council in 1958, during the presidency of Dr. Carlyle Adams, the organization consisted of divisions based on geographic proximity; and departments which acted as administrative units or as liaisons to the semi-autonomous organizations which provide services to the community under joint auspices. These were separated into: Program Departments of Community Ministry, Hospital Ministry, Student Work, Christian Education, Social Education and Action, and Evangelism; General Departments of United Church Women, United Church Men, and Ministers' Association; and Central Departments such as Business and Finance and Public Relations. Current structure provides for standing committees which include the Executive Committee, Nominating Committee, Finance Committee and the Personnel Committee. Previously existing geographic divisions are not specified as of the 1980 Revised Constitution.
Presidents:
1941-1942 Mr. Winthrop P. Stevens
1942-1943 Rev. Brewer Burnett
1943-1945 Rev. William McConaghy
1945-1947 Rev. Hobart F. Goewey
1947-1949 Rev. Arthur M. Adams
1949-1950 Rev. Erville B. Maynard
1950-52 Rev. Arthur F. Jennings
1952-1954 Rev. Dr. Russell G. Ganzele
1954-1956 Rev. Ross Blake
1956-1958 Mr. Russel H. Broughton
1958-1960 Rev. Dr. Carlyle Adams
1960-1961 Rev. Harold Griffis
1961-1963 Rev. Dr. LeRoy C. Brandt
1963-1965 Dr. Milton C. Olson
1965-1966 Rev. Dr. Norman E. Thomas
1966-1968 Rev. Ralph M. Carmichael
1968-1969 Rev. W. Bernard Grossamn
1969-1970 Rev. Dr. Robert C. Lamar
1970-1972 Rev. Ralph H. Elliot
1972-1973 Rev. Louis Brewer
1973-1975 Rev. Robert B. Thomas
1975-1977 Rev. Bruce Miller
1977-1979 Rev. Richard B. Hunter
1979-1982 Rev. Craig Bartholomew
1982-1984 Rev. William Roland
1984-1986 Mr. Joseph Lynn, Jr.
1986-1988 Hon. Morton M. Z. Lynn
1988-1991 Mrs. Evelyn C. Stone
1991-1993 Rev. Dr. S. Albert Newman
1993-1995 Rev. Fred Shilling
1995-1997 Rev. Allan Janssen
1997 Rev. Edgar N. Kemp, Jr.
1997-1999 Marlene Shilling
2000-2001 Harold R. Howes
2001-2002 Rev. William Cotant
Executive Directors
Richard Morford
Harvey W. Hollis
Richard Norman Hughes
Vladimir Hartman
Joyce Steinkraus Giles
James H. Snedeker, Jr., Interim
Fred Shilling
James H. Snedeker, Jr., Interim
Edgar N. Kemp, Jr.
Robert C. Lamar
John U. Miller
Scope and Content Information
The majority of records in this collection are board minutes (with organizational constitutions, Director's Reports, and some committee minutes) reports, newsletters, administrative files, subject files, and some correspondence. There is also a collection of clippings from local newspapers.
Well structured documentation, in the form of meeting minutes, of the formative period of the organization allow for a determination of the principle factors, both human and situational, for the genesis of the CACC. There are numerous sources (minutes, newsletters, annual reports) of the names of individuals and the roles they played in the organization; names, locations, size, relative prosperity and denomination of member congregations; and information pertaining to the other groups, individuals, and organizations which provided services in the Capital District.
Many of the records show the degree to which the organization was concerned and involved with issues and events of local, national and international concern including World War II, the anti-Communist fervor, the Civil Rights Movement, the Abortion debate, the evolution of the State University of New York system, urban blight, and fair housing.
Early correspondence was not usually kept or was only occasionally filed with the meeting minutes at which the subject matter was discussed. Several references are made to a city-wide survey conducted in the summer of 1946 to determine area residents' religious denomination and to which congregation (if any) they belonged. However, no results of these efforts has been located beyond a January 1947 mention that the report of the findings is not yet ready.
A mention in correspondence is made of a visit to the area of the Reverend Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. on June 14, 1961. Regrettably, there is no further mention of the planned speaking engagement, nor a report of it in meeting minutes or subject files. There are numerous gaps in the coverage of newsletters, annual reports and meeting minutes. These sometimes occur at times when social issues (such as civil rights) were most likely occupying the efforts and energies of Council personnel. Unfortunately, it is these times when records of events and issues, as they affected this organization, would be most valuable.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into five series.
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1941-2002, 2.4 cubic ft.
Series 2: Correspondence, 1947-1988, .4 cubic ft.
Series 3: Newsletters, 1948-2003, .6 cubic ft.
Series 4: Subject Files, 1953-1989, 3.6 cubic ft.
Series 5: Meeting Minutes, 1941-1987, 2.0 cubic ft.
Series 1, 2 and 4 are arranged alphabetically. Series 3 and 5 are arranged chronologically.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Africana Studies; Africana Studies
Subject and Genre Headings
The Capital Area Council of Churches; Churches--New York (State)--Albany (N.Y.); Church councils; Albany (N.Y.); Annual reports; Newsletters; Administrative records; Minutes; Financial records
Container List
- Administrative Files, 1941-2002; 1; 2.4
  Arranged alphabetically.
  The Administrative Files follow standard practice using the name of report type, originating committee, special event or external entity as the subject heading. The deepest historical contents are found in folders for Annual Reports (beginning 1944), Black Book (1945-56), Budgets (1954-56), Federation Membership (1947-51), Membership Committee (1942-47), and Organization of the Federation (1941-48). It should be noted that much financial, membership and special events information not included in these Administrative Files can be found filed with the Meeting Minutes at which the topic or report was discussed or in the Annual Reports.
  Of notable length are the holdings of Annual Reports, which cover the years from 1944 - 2002 (missing are 45-46, 48-52, 53-54 and 1980). These consist of the year-end reports from the President and Executive Director; summary reports of the major standing and special events committees; and Treasurer's report and budget as presented to the Annual Assemblies. The financial reports contained therein include the past year's income and expenses including support received from each member congregation (grouped by denomination). A calendar of upcoming events for the year is also presented, as are award and scholarship recipient's names. The Annual Reports also include a full listing of nominated officers and board members for the forthcoming year containing full name and church community to which they belong. Anniversary year's reports from 1981, 1990, and 2000 include reflections, summaries and histories.
  - Addresses for Mailing, 1959-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Endowment Fund, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meetings, 1961-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Report, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual Report, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual Report, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual Report, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual Report, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annual Report, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annual Report, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Annual Report, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annual Report, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annual Report, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual Report, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annual Report, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Annual Report, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Annual Report, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Annual Report, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Annual Report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Annual Report, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Annual Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Annual Report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Annual Report, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Annual Report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Annual Report, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Annual Report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Annual Report, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Annual Report, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Annual Report, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Annual Report, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Annual Report, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Annual Report, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Annual Report, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Annual Report, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Annual Report, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Annual Report, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Annual Report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Annual Report, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Annual Report, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Annual Report, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Annual Report, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Applications for Membership in Council, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Assembly Meeting, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Assembly Meetings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Assembly Meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Black Book, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Correspondence, 1947-1988; 2; 0.4
  Most of the correspondence in this series (with a few exceptions) is from the 1980s during the directorships of Joyce Steinkraus Giles and James H. Snedeker, Jr.. Most earlier materials were filed with the meeting minutes or with the subject files to which they pertain. Much of the included materials consist of letters sent by individual contributors (usually along with a donation) and letters and faxes between CACC and other local service organizations, clergy members and political leaders.
  Topics center around thank you letters; invitations to special events; requests for support of new or ongoing Council initiatives and programs; activities related to the protests against Apartheid in South Africa; family planning issues; and building / facility usage.
  Folder 19 (Outgoing, 1986-1987) includes a "Policy Option Ballot" for then-current topics on U.S. Central American policy from the Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies, Washington, D.C.; and a letter from the National Council of Churches concerning guidelines for new Social Security Administration policies pertaining to ordained ministers (May 2, 1956) as well as official brochures from the Social Security administration regarding the changes.
  Featured among correspondents are The Hon. Erastus Corning II (1909 - 1983), Mayor of Albany from 1942 - 1983; The Most Rev. Howard Hubbard, Roman Catholic Bishop of Albany from 1977 to the present; and Dr. Henry Pitney Van Dusen (1897 - 1975), President of New York's Union Theological Seminary from 1945 - 1963 (correspondence includes Van Dusen's resume as of 1947 - Folder 16). Others include clergy of member churches, health care facility directors, and state and national affiliated organizations
  - A, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - C, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-In, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - F, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - G, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - H, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - K, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - L, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Pastors, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lynn, Morton M.Z, President CACC, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - M, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1947; 1952-1953; 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - N, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - O, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Outgoing, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - P-Q, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - R, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - S, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Social Security, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - T, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - U, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - V, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - W, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - X, Y, Z, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Newsletters, 1948-2003; 3; 0.6
  Arranged chronologically.
  Early examples of the monthly newsletters are sparse with some years being represented by a single month's edition. Evidence that a letter was definitely produced every month without fail is not forthcoming, and thus the included examples could be exhaustive. Contents typically include sections on seasonal celebrations; announcements from various committees and sub-groups; upcoming special events information (or reports on those past); and in early examples, listings of recommended radio programs and new books on matters of faith.